<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good nevves from all quarters of the kingdome; particularly from Gloucester. The more strange for the noveltie; first printed, and at that time when the adversary was storming that citie; and yet more strange, for its antiquitie, because assured us by a word, more stable than the earth or heaven; and by a letter of ancient date, sent to Hezekiah King of Judah. Wee have the same assurance also touching a strange destruction to the wicked, specially to those princes all, who have filled the land with bloud, that those shall not dye the common death, nor be visited after the visitation of all men, because they have done more wickedly then ever any princes before them. ... Published for the comfort of all the Godly, in all the quarters of the world, by speciall licence from their Court-booke, September 12. 1643.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E250_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E250_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871141</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159075</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159075)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 43:E250[9] or 43:E250[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good nevves from all quarters of the kingdome; particularly from Gloucester. The more strange for the noveltie; first printed, and at that time when the adversary was storming that citie; and yet more strange, for its antiquitie, because assured us by a word, more stable than the earth or heaven; and by a letter of ancient date, sent to Hezekiah King of Judah. Wee have the same assurance also touching a strange destruction to the wicked, specially to those princes all, who have filled the land with bloud, that those shall not dye the common death, nor be visited after the visitation of all men, because they have done more wickedly then ever any princes before them. ... Published for the comfort of all the Godly, in all the quarters of the world, by speciall licence from their Court-booke, September 12. 1643.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Paine and M. Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>September 13. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Oxfords Latin rimes turned into English reason" has separate register and pagination and is identified as E.250[10].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gloucester (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159075:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>OXFORDS</hi> LATIN RIMES TVRNED INTO ENGLISH REASON.
<hi>OR</hi> Horrid Blaſphemy made excellent Divinitie, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to give the
Righteous aſſured confidence for ever; That, though the Adverſary
(ſeemes) to command the <hi>meanes,</hi> yet God commands the <hi>end;</hi>
and <hi>prayer</hi> commands God: Therefore, what ever the
<hi>premiſſes</hi> are, the concluſion will be glorious, and the News
very good from all thoſe <hi>Quarters, North, South,</hi> and
<hi>Weſt,</hi> where the Adverſary boaſteth of his ſucceſſe: But
from <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> beſt of all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
there the Adverſary hath blaſphemed the <hi>Holy One,</hi> and is mad with
rage againſt His <hi>Holy Ones.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q> 
                  <p>Then ſhall the <hi>Lord</hi> be jealous for his Land, and
pittie his people,</p>
                  <bibl>Joel 2.18.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <p>Thou haſt ſeene it: The poore committeth himſelfe unto
Thee, &amp;c.</p>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 10.14.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <p>Iudgements are prepared for ſcorners, and ſtripes for the
back of fooles,</p>
                  <bibl>Pro. 19.29.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Bſerving ſome picking in the duſt-heaps; others raking the
channells in the ſtreets and ſinkes in the Kitchin, where they have found
precious matter ſometimes, moſt times that, which hath recompenced their
labour: I muſt obſerve herefrom, That no place, nor perſon is ſo
barren, but may yeeld ſome fruit: Nay nothing, no not that dung, which is
moſt unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe it is the corruption of that which is beſt,
but hath vertue in it, more then is ordinarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſaith a great 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> ſayes thus to an
idle and uſeles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; Thou art of much leſſe uſe, then is thy
dung: not worthy of that worſt excrement (in thy conceipt) which thou
voydeſt. <hi>Quae Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur,</hi> things we tread un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-foot, or leave
there, would be of good eſteem, if we knew the uſe of them; this uſe is
ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to the world, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent matters, by Mr.
<hi>Plats,</hi> whom I know one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Bookes, a man of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious uſe and
abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> Schollar.</p>
            <p>Let not the Reader then be diſcouraged at the ſight of the
<hi>Rimes,</hi> which ſhall now be preſented to his eye, though, indeed,
they ſmell more of the <hi>Pot,</hi> then of the <hi>Poet:</hi> and
becauſe, probably, they came from <hi>Oxford,</hi> from whence wee can expect
no good; for there Sathan hath his Throne, and Iniquitie hath been
eſtabliſhed by a Law. True it is, I have as vile an eſteeme of the
Verſes and the Poet, as he hath of his owne dung; and yet, ſith there can
be vertue extracted thence, even out of that dung, The Reader need not doubt,
but when I have raked them to the bottom, I ſay to the bottom, I ſhall
finde ſome vertue there, ſome excellent Truth uttered by him as a
<hi>ſcorne,</hi> and as through a <hi>Trunke,</hi> but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king very much for
the eſtabliſhment of the Righteous, whom the <hi>fool ſcorneth.</hi> I
ſhall ſay more to the <hi>ſcorn,</hi> for that is my maine ſcope, no
more to the <hi>ſcorners</hi> but this, which is enough to make them
trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. 
<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 3.34. Pro. 29.8</note>
               <hi>Surely the
Lord ſcorneth the ſcorners, for they bring a Citie into a ſnare:</hi> Nay
they ſet a Citie on 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flant.</hi>
               </note>
fire; The Lord will perſecute them <hi>with his ſtorme,</hi> and take them
away with his <hi>whirlewinde,</hi> if they repent not: So leaving the
<hi>ſcorners,</hi> I come to their <hi>ſcorne,</hi> which is wrapt up in
theſe Verſes, fifteen in number.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>Extincta Caſtro fax pulchra novo est,</l> 
               <l>Nec nautae poſtea, nec militi</l> 
               <l>Sit noto Pharos. Auſter diſparem,</l> 
               <l>Haud tulit Caſum: murus, cui addita est</l> 
               <l>Canina Litera, merſa est ſuis</l> 
               <l>Cum turmis nuper Leporis vado.</l> 
               <l>Euri <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Briſtonia</l> 
               <l>Leporinos Horreſcens vortices.</l> 
               <l>Anglica Claudij timet Pares</l> 
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs Caſus: Haerois Teutonici</l> 
               <l>Myrmidones aſtant magno cum duce.</l> 
               <l>Pacata Thule eſt; nec Noto timor.</l> 
               <l>Popello aut Regi: Nihil relictum eſt</l> 
               <l>Brittannicum domare Caeſarem,</l> 
               <l>Ni <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> preces
gregis.</l> 
               <l>Haec Sphinges raptim Oedipo ſuo,</l>
               <bibl>
                  <date>Julij 20.
1643.</date>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>This laſt verſe ſhewes the Poet to be a <hi>merry
Greeke;</hi> but in the cloſe wee ſhall ſay of his <hi>laughter,</hi>
               <hi>It is 
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 2.2.</note> mad.</hi> In my
tranſlation I ſhall render the words firſt, then the ſenſe and
meaning; not to the Poets liking ſure. I have not learnt of the Devill, his
Maſter, to play the <hi>fool,</hi> or the knave, or the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159075:2"/>I thanke God, who hath given me more grace, I have not ſold
my ſelfe to doe evill, for then I could, as he, and the <hi>Court</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Greek &amp; Latin Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets tell us of one
<hi>Mercury,</hi> a very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous perſon, a notable <hi>knave,</hi> a
cunning <hi>thiefe,</hi> and a moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar,</hi> not his like
in all the world; he was the <hi>Court-Mercury</hi> too; which may ſatiſfie
the world touching the <hi>Court</hi> then, and this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Syr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named
<hi>Mercurius Auli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi>
now.</note> 
               <hi>Mercury,</hi> upon the Ale-bench, <hi>make ſongs of
David;</hi> I could (for I know their way well enough) give-up my tongue, and
my Pen, to the Devills forge, intreat him to ſharpen them againſt the
<hi>face of the Righteous;</hi> The Devill would gratifie me ſo farre, he
would enable me, as well as them, natures bent being that way, to lie and
raile, and blaſpheme; he would procure me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for doing him ſervice,
ſome high degree in the Schooles, good gaine to my purſe, haply ſome
place or title of honour, for ſuch ſervants are in the onely ready way to
riſe in the world; But then I ſhould render my ſelfe a <hi>fool,</hi> and
a <hi>knave</hi> both, and in every ſober mans conſtruction, <hi>mad</hi>
alſo, as the newes from <hi>Oxford</hi> once a fortnight renders their
<hi>Mercury</hi> there, and as theſe verſes render the Poet here; All of
the eaſieſt conſtruction, eſpecially the firſt, becauſe of the
agreement it hath with the Engliſh, wherein I had pretty skill ever ſince I
could read latin, for thus I could interpret this verſe in <hi>Ovid, Tacturos
ſydera ſumma putes, Thou ſhalt put ſummer ſyder into tanckards.</hi>
Such a conſtruction the childe makes here, and yet he thinkes he hath
propoſed a Riddle, which needs an <hi>Oedipus;</hi> no, it needs not, for</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Extincta Caſtro fax pulchra novo est; nec nautae poſtea,
nec militi ſit noto Pharos;] Pulchra fax,</hi> is the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi>
(a bright ſtarre indeed, but of that anon,) and <hi>Caſtro novo</hi> is by
<hi>Newca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> he meanes the good <hi>Earle</hi> there, and his meaning
is very proper, for he hath no more ſenſe of <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>goodneſſe,</hi> then have the timber and ſtones in that Caſtle; But
we muſt not ſtifle the birth, or the Poets witty conception, which is this;
That the bright ſtarre in the <hi>North,</hi> is quite extinct now by
<hi>New-Castle,</hi> and ſhall be of no more uſe to Souldier or Mariner.
<hi>Auſter diſparem haud tulit caſum.</hi> As this in the <hi>North,</hi>
ſo the like diſaſter hath befallen the Roundheads in the <hi>South;</hi>
for <hi>Murus cui addita eſt Canina litera, merſa eſt ſuis cum turmis
nuper leporis vado:</hi> I have <hi>plowed with the Poets heifer,</hi> and can
reade his Riddle; Sure <hi>Murus</hi> is a wall; So ſure <hi>Canina
litera,</hi> is <hi>R,</hi> as they ſay in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> where they
<hi>make a noice like a dog, and goe round about the Citie.</hi> But here is a
deepe conceipt, for as <hi>Caſtro novo,</hi> in the firſt verſe, is an
<hi>Earle:</hi> ſo <hi>Murus,</hi> in the fourth verſe, is ſome excellent
Perſon ſure, precious in the eyes of God and men; for this ſhall be
ſpoken to the eternall reproach of <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Perſons there; That
they have vilified and reproached thoſe, whom God will honour; and they have
honoured thoſe with degrees in Schooles, and titles of honour, whom
<hi>God</hi> doth account as vile, as they can eſteeme their owne dung; Had I
heard no more but this, That the man is blaſphemed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> I
muſt conclude preſently, as every ſober man will; <hi>This is ſome
excellent Perſon,</hi> he hath done <hi>worthily,</hi> he is become
<hi>famous,</hi> I know he is, for he is <hi>infamous</hi> in <hi>Oxford;</hi>
There the drunkards make their ſongs of him, and there they make <hi>a noice
like a dog.</hi> I proceed, <hi>Leporis</hi> of a hare, <hi>vado</hi> in a
ſhallow water, which you may <hi>ford-over;</hi> put together, it is in
<hi>Hare-ford,</hi> and the literall Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; That the <hi>wall</hi>
and all about it, was drowned in <hi>Hare-ford:</hi> The Allegoricall is this,
and it is very witty in the Poets conceipt, <hi>That Sir William Waller, with
all his Troopes, were ſwallowed up quick in Hare-ford,</hi> i. e. by the
<hi>Earle of Hartford;</hi> And ſo the Poet hath added a letter to
<hi>Murus,</hi> and that is ever an addition to a Bleſſing: and hath taken
away a letter from his Lordſhips title of honour, which ever, in ſacred
account, makes an addition to a curſe. It followes,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euri <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
Briſtonia, Leporinos Horreſcens vortices</hi> (i. e.) That ſhallow water
<hi>fordable</hi> but now, is now raiſed to ſuch an height, that
<hi>Bristol</hi> is ſwallowed up by the proud ſwelling waters of
<hi>Hare-ford.</hi> This interpretation is literall too, and Allegoricall; one
word onely is out of place, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, for it fits not the Allegory, yet is
it very emphaticall; <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Briſtonia, Bristoll groanes under cruell bondage;</hi> It does indeed, ſuch
as <hi>Iſrael</hi> never felt under <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his Task-maſters;
nor the Chriſtian under the Turke; <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Briſtonia,</hi> That Citie knowes the
<hi>ſenſe</hi> of that word now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anglica claudij timet pares urbs Caſus</hi> (i. e.) And
<hi>Glouceſter</hi> lyes now at the mouth of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring floud: for
<hi>Haerois Teutoni i</hi> Myrmidones, The <hi>Myrmidons</hi> [theſe were the
moſt bloudy <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages,</hi> that any hiſtory makes mention of, ſo
hardened and <hi>brawned</hi> in villanies, and bloudy executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they
became a Proverb; a very fit word here to declare unto us, what is cleare
enough, the more then barbarous uſages and inſolencies of thoſe Rogues,
Theeves, Robbers, Murtherers, Beaſts in the ſhape of Men, the Souldiers] of
the <hi>German Peer,</hi> have begirt that Citie, with their great
<hi>Duke.</hi> The Poet meanes thoſe <hi>two, Brethren in evill,</hi> whom he
dignifies as he thinkes fit, but God knowes, they who are highly eſteemed in
<hi>Oxford,</hi> are an abomination in the ſight of God Their ſword hath
made women childleſſe; It may be the <hi>Lord</hi> will be ſo gracious to
them, that their Mother ſhall not be childleſſe amongſt women. They
have committed lewdneſſe in <hi>Iſraels</hi> land, <hi>Gods land:</hi> It
may be their land ſhall proſper, and they ſhall live to eat the fruits
thereof. They have done their utmoſt to ruine thoſe, and their houſe, who
layed out themſelves, for the building up of the <hi>Palatine</hi> houſe:
This horrid ingratitude, this requitall of kindneſſe, is no ſin in
<hi>Gods</hi> account; He is mercifull; It may be, the <hi>Lord</hi> will
<hi>build theſe men a ſure houſe:</hi> They ſhall live out all their
dayes, and when they dye,<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159075:2"/>they ſhall dye as other men, and
be buried as thoſe, who are precious in Gods account. But there is no
truſting to it; we have not a <hi>word</hi> for it; againſt it we have, for
this is the <hi>word,</hi> and <hi>burden</hi> from the <hi>Lord,</hi>
againſt all thoſe that have ſhed bloud to their power; 
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 55.23</note>
               <hi>Bloudy and
deceitfull men ſhall not live out halfe their dayes; Thou ſhalt
not be joyned with them in buriall, becauſe thou haſt deſtroyed</hi>
(<note n="*" place="margin">So we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Poſſeſſive
<hi>(Thy)</hi> and not that he laid his own Land waſte, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a
<hi>Babel.</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels kings did ſo, and the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
in name: as the Sacred &amp; French Chronicles tell us, and as our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
will reade more at large in after times. Theſe ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures will add waight
to the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Lord. Pſal. 5.6. Pſal. 11.5. Pro. 22.23
&amp; 23.11. Iſa. 49.12. Zac. 14.12</note>thy) <hi>land, and ſlaine</hi>
(thy) <hi>People</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 14.20.</note> [againſt whom
the Lord was a little <hi>diſpleaſed, and Babylon helped for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the 
<note n="*" place="margin">Zech 1.15</note> affliction</hi>]. What
the Poet ſayes now is of ſmall account, <hi>Thus ſayes the Lord,</hi> (as
we have read) and this the Burden from his mouth, upon thoſe <hi>great
Captains</hi> &amp; their <hi>Myrmidones.</hi> I proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pacata Thule eſt; Scotland</hi> is quiet (ſayes
<hi>Oxford</hi> Poet, I ſhall ſay more to that anon) <hi>Nec noto ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
Popello aut Regi,</hi> nor is there any feare from the <hi>North,</hi> but that
all there abouts will come forth to the Kings foot, and be trod under, as
<hi>the mire in the ſtreets;</hi> for (mark it) <hi>nihil relictum est
Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannicum domare Caeſarem;</hi> There is no let in the world whereby to
keepe downe <hi>Caeſar</hi> (the King) from [aſcending above <hi>the height
of the Clouds, and] being [like the moſt High,]</hi> an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,
whoſe Rule is his <hi>will</hi> [it had need be an <hi>holy will,</hi> but
ſuch is onely Gods <hi>will</hi>] nothing can hinder this now, now that
<hi>New-Caſtle</hi> hath put out the ſtarre in the <hi>North;
Hare-ford</hi> hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed the <hi>wall</hi> in the <hi>South,</hi> and
the two Brothers are ſo proſperous in the <hi>Weſt;</hi> nothing can
hinder now, but <hi>Preces gregis,</hi> the prayers of a poore flock [of
ſheepe, <hi>Armenta</hi> and <hi>Pecora,</hi> are great Cattle ever, 
<note n="*" place="margin">Amo. 4.1</note>
               <hi>The Bulls and kine of
Baſhan, which oppreſſe the poore, which cruſh the needy,</hi>
(<hi>Gregis</hi> is of a flock of ſheep]
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, newly fallen mad; he meanes a
poore deſpicable, helpleſſe, (I doe not ſay hopeleſſe) deſtitute,
caſt out, fatherleſſe People, a People vile in their owne eyes, (but of
high account with God. Theſe he meanes; Then his meaning is, nothing remaines
now that <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> is ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and ſtrong;
<hi>Hare-fords</hi> waters ſo riſen, ſwelled ſo high, and
ſtorme-like, ſwallowing-up, and <hi>ſtorming</hi> all before it, and
leaving no food behind it; Now that the two <hi>Roaring Lyons</hi> [the Lord
calls them 
<note n="*" place="margin">Zeph. 3.3</note> ſo, and I dare not
thinke of a fitter expreſſion] have their mouths wide open to ſwallow-up
<hi>Glouceſter,</hi> the Inhabitants there, and all about; nothing remaines
now to ſave theſe <hi>poore flock</hi> from theſe Devourers,
<hi>Niſi,</hi> but, <hi>The prayers of the poore of the flock,</hi> a poore,
deſtitute, caſt-out People. Well, bleſſed be God, theſe people have,
<hi>But</hi> their Adverſaries allowance, and yet they have enough! yes,
enough and enough, for they have <hi>All,</hi> God and 
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 33.11.</note>
               <hi>All; Enough</hi>
then, though (which I will adde) all the Adverſaries Brethren, the Kings good
Subjects in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (theſe were called horrid Rebells an yeare and
halfe agoe in a Court Complement) though theſe are called over to doe their
King the like good ſervice here, which they have done him in
<hi>Ireland;</hi> yet theſe people have <hi>enough,</hi> though but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
their Adverſaries allowance: and they can, though they are, as
<hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> were, 
<note n="*" place="margin">Neh. 1.4 2.1.</note>
               <hi>ſad, faint,</hi>
and 
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan 8.27.</note>
               <hi>ſicke</hi> alſo,
becauſe of what they heare and ſee, yet they can recover themſelves, and
rejoyce in their portion. They have a <hi>God</hi> to goe unto, (when I have
ſaid <hi>God,</hi> I have ſaid All) The wrath of man ſhall praiſe him;
The treachery of man ſhall advance his faithfulneſſe, as the
weakneſſe, fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and wickedneſſe of man doth advance the
power, wiſdome, and goodneſſe of God. The Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary with all their
counſell and ſtrength muſt fall before the <hi>hand lifted-up,</hi> for
it is lifted up to the moſt high God, God of Hoſts, King of Saints. They
can pray unto him, commit all their concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto the boſom of a Father,
who is then neareſt to his Children, the nearer danger is. Prayers ſhall
turn all this to the furtherance of the Goſpel, and the increaſe of the
Churches joy. The Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary may have ſo much power, as to reſtraine Sea
and Land both, and ſet open the gates of Hell againſt the Church; He cannot
reſtraine prayer, which openeth the treaſury of Heaven, and commands God
there, as we ſhall ſee preſently. Bleſſed be God, the Father of our
Lord Jeſus Chriſt; He ſuffers his peoples adverſaries to carve forth
his Childrens portion, and behold it a large portion. The Adverſary now has
aſſigned a Sanctuary to the people of God, a place of Refuge indeed, a
ſtrong Tower, the <hi>Name of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Righteous fly unto it,
and they are 
<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 18.10.</note> ſafe.</hi> Nothing
remaines now, whereby to ſave theſe people from falling into the mouth of
the devourer, but the prayers of the deſtitute, that is enough, till that
Refuge faileth, the hearts of the Righteous cannot faile; But that refuge never
fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>In the Lord Jehovah, is everlaſting 
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 26.4.</note> ſtrength,</hi> an
everlaſting ground for everlaſting confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; 
<q rend="inline">"To eſtabliſh the Righteous now &amp;
evermore, on this foundation, That the <hi>iſſue</hi> or <hi>end</hi> will
be <hi>good;</hi> the wicked connot over-rule there, the <hi>end</hi> is out of
their ſpheare, that God makes, He is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter 
<note n="*" place="margin">James 5.11.</note> there. The King could
purſue <hi>Iſrael</hi> with deadly hatred, he could ſpeak 
<note n="*" place="margin">Exo 15.9</note> proudly, but he could
not overtake <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Another King, as proud as the former, could, in
his rage, command the furnace to be heated ſeven-times hotter then 
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 3.19. Ver. 25.</note> ordinary; he
could not command the <hi>end,</hi> not make the fire burn, there <hi>God</hi>
over-ruled; The ſervants of the 
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.34.</note>
                  <hi>Lord quenched the
violence of the flame.</hi> What ever the <hi>Premiſſes</hi> are, which the
wicked have made, how agreeable ſoever to their ſenſe and reaſon, yet
they can <hi>do no more,</hi> God will draw the Concluſion evermore by ſuch
a kinde of <hi>Logick,</hi> as ſenſe and reaſon, the Philoſophy of the
world, is not acquainted with, onely God knows, and in his favour, he has made
his Children know it, &amp; given them aſſurance touching that matter, and
ſo they lye at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159075:3"/>in God, confident under his
ſhadow.</q> Reſolved fully at this high point, <hi>That God commands the
end, and Prayer commands God.</hi> And this bids the people of God, expect good
newes from all Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yea out of the <hi>Weſt</hi> alſo, where the
Churches Sunne ſeemed to ſet. Behold then, the Poet does <hi>belch</hi> out
a double Blaſphemy; whence I ſhall draw a double Concluſion, &amp; make
it Chriſtian Divinitie.</p>
            <q> 
               <list>
                  <item>1. "That Prayers, which the Poet accounts <hi>a
nothing,</hi> but (i.e.) a thing of no account, are of high account with God,
and the great Confidence of the godly.</item>
                  <item> 2. "That thoſe he accounts <hi>mad</hi> people, are the
onely ſober men in the world. I will enlarge upon the firſt, but firſt I
will explain it.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>Whereas I ſaid, Prayers are of high account with God, and very
efficacious to bring to paſſe all the Churches deſignes, and to
fruſtrate the Adverſaries; That is true enough, there can be no miſtake
there; for the Adverſary meanes, the Prayers of a deſtitute People, theirs
I ſay, and he muſt ſay ſo too, who have a <hi>Father</hi> to goe unto,
and an <hi>Advocate with that Father.</hi> It is very notable; If they have a
potent <hi>Advocate</hi> with an Adverſary, they have an <hi>hope</hi> to
prevaile: but having an <hi>Advocate with their Father,</hi> they can have no
doubt; <hi>Wee have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Christ the 
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.1.</note> Righteous.</hi> There
can be no miſtake there, Prayers are very prevailing, there is in them an
<hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency,</hi> they command God, therefore are prayers <hi>the great
Confidence of the godly.</hi> But here we muſt be informed, prayers are ſo
indeed, not conſidered in themſelves: Alas no, the good mans confidence
muſt be that which is perfection it ſelfe, compleat, and perfectly perfect:
There is nothing ſo <hi>perfect,</hi> but Jeſus Chriſt, and
juſtification by him; Therefore to build our Confidence upon
<hi>Prayers,</hi> conſidered as a dutie onely, and no more, is <hi>to build a
Tower upon an Oaten ſtraw.</hi> This then is the meaning, <hi>Prayers are a
godly mans great Confidence,</hi> as they cloſe with a Promiſe, and make
the ſoule cling and cleave to Chriſt. As prayer puts the ſoul into a
ſure hand, the hand of a <hi>Mediator, The Amen, The Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and true
Witnes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.7.14.</note> He that <hi>is holy, He that
is true, &amp;c.</hi> In that hand the Soul and all her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, all her
prayers touching that matter, concerning her particular well fare or the
Churches, there the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are ſafe, and
thence they ſhall receive Anſwer in the fitteſt time, a gracious, yea a
glorious <hi>end.</hi> And ſo Prayers are a godly Mans Confidence. And ſo
much for Explication, and Confirmation of the point. Now we will read the
<hi>Experiences</hi> of the godly in all ages, touching this matter, That we
may ſee, that which is of the vileſt account with vile men, is of the
higheſt account with God, and good men <hi>I gave my ſelfe to 
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 109.4</note> Prayer,</hi> ſayes
<hi>David,</hi> (i.e.) he made prayer his worke, when he was in a very ſad
and unſetled caſe, <hi>Toſſed up and 
<note n="*" place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> down as a Locust</hi>
(a very fit Emblem of the Church, the tides and changes of her affaires,
<hi>up</hi> and <hi>downe</hi>) then he gave <hi>himſelfe to Prayer,</hi> and
this fixed him, made him <hi>a quiet 
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 33.20.</note> habitation,</hi> who
was before as unſtable as a <hi>Graſhopper,</hi> and gave him aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
confidence, that the <hi>end</hi> muſt be good, ſo he ends with praiſe,
<hi>I will greatly praiſe the Lord, &amp;c. David</hi> ſets downe two
<hi>experiments</hi> he had made of this, I will mention no more, becauſe
theſe are moſt notable, how he confounded <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and (that)
<hi>Counſell</hi> (all for warre) which was as an <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.</note> While his mighty Adverſary
curſed, <hi>David</hi> prayed, cloſed with an Almightie Arme, <hi>So</hi>
his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary fell before his face, and his owne ſword cut his throat. At
another time, a great Counſellour diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted <hi>David</hi> (as the
manner is) when he ſaw that, he gave himſelf to Prayer, as his manner was,
<hi>Lord</hi> ſayes he, <hi>I pray thee turn the Counſell of Ahitophel into
fooliſhnes</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.31.</note> No ſooner asked, but
it was done; <hi>The Lord defeated the good Counſell of Ahitophel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.14.</note> (good to bring about the horrid deſigne
againſt <hi>David,</hi> the dethroning of him) and when he ſaw his Councell
was not followed, wee know what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, <hi>He teareth h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mſelfe in his anger,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Bildad,</hi> [but his application was wrong] <hi>his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell caſt
him downe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 18 4.7.8.</note> The Concluſion
then ſtands firme, <hi>Prayers are a godly Mans Confidence</hi> (as before
expounded) he is aſſured fully theſe will <hi>wheel</hi> all about,
<hi>turn the Scene</hi> (where now we ſee nothing but drawne ſwords bathed
in bloud) the <hi>end</hi> ſhall be gladſome, a glorious deliverance at the
laſt. The poore People have put up Prayers to their Father, they ſhall be
delivered-<hi>out,</hi> ſuſtained-<hi>in,</hi> or preſerved <hi>by</hi>
the Judgement; For the Devourers mouth, which ſeemed to ſwallow-up, did
carry <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> ſafe to land: I ſaid, <hi>preſerved by the
Iudgement,</hi> delivered by that, which ſeemes to the eye, an
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on. <hi>A few were ſaved by
water;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.20.</note> That water which drowned
others ſaved a <hi>few.</hi> I know it does relate to <hi>Baptiſme;</hi>
but we may apply it to the <hi>waters of affliction,</hi> wherein the wicked
are drowned, but the Righteous are ſaved: The Lord will have <hi>reſpect to
the Prayers of his ſervants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 8.28.</note>
which they put up unto Him day and night I will make a ſhort account of a
rich Treaſury. I could ſay as much of <hi>Prayer,</hi> as is ſaid of
<hi>Faith;</hi> By prayer <hi>Abraham</hi> obtained as much as he deſired; So
<hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſo <hi>Jacob:</hi> Looke how wide Faith opened their
mouths, ſo they were filled By prayer <hi>Moſes</hi> tyed Gods hand,
<hi>Let me alone Moſes,</hi> ſayes God, No, but he would not; A poore weake
man overcomes the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God. <hi>Moſes</hi> did more then
<hi>Ioſhuah</hi> did,<note place="margin">Joſh 10 12.</note> he commanded the
Sunne and the Moone, (which is very notable) <hi>Moſes commanded God;</hi> He
was pleaſed to be <hi>commanded ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa.
45.11.</note> to tell his People how <hi>command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> a thing Prayer is. It
is the moſt efficacious of any thing in Heaven or Earth; It has the
quickeſt<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159075:3"/>motion, and as quick a returne: I meane ſtill,
the prayer of the deſtitute, (a people looſe from, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of all
humane help) for their prayer is <hi>powred forth now.</hi> The eye is ſingle
towards God, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly ſet Heaven-wards: The extremitie is great, the
Adverſaries pride at the higheſt peg, the people of God at the loweſt
<hi>eb,</hi> in a periſhing condition, <hi>Refuge faileth,</hi> they are
importunate, they will give <hi>God no reſt;</hi> then God hearkens and
heares, then the <hi>return</hi> is quick and ſpeedy. For there is no
<hi>help on earth.</hi> Now mark it evermore, <hi>He ſhall ſend from Heaven
and ſave me,</hi> ſayes <hi>David</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
75.3.</note> in his <hi>Mictham,</hi> words worthy to be written in golden
Letters, when there is no help in earth, <hi>He ſhall ſend from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and
ſave mee;</hi> The Churches confidence for ever. I will skip over a large
Chronicle, and obſerve onely one prayer there, King <hi>Hezeckiah</hi> is
greatly diſtreſſed, A proud Adverſary has begirt the Citie round; And
now, <hi>There is but one thing remaines,</hi> which the King can doe for his
ſecuritie, and that he does, he falls downe upon his knees, <hi>Spreads the
Letter,</hi> the rebukes, the blaſphemies, the great ſtraights, he and his
people were in; all this he ſpreads beford the <hi>Lord,</hi> and he calls-in
for help, ſends Meſſengers to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> tells him, there is but
one way to take (a ſure way) to goe to God by <hi>Prayer,</hi> O let us not
neglect that way; Wherefore lift-up <hi>thy Prayer for the remnant that are
left.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 19.4.</note> Sith there is but one way
left open, let us preſſe-on in it, and weary the <hi>Lord</hi> with
importunitie. Now what ſayes the <hi>Lord? That which thou haſt
prayed to Me, againſt Senacherib King of Aſſyria, I have heard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 19.20.</note> There was a quick <hi>Returne,</hi> and the
execution is as quick, for the next Newes we reade, is, 
<q rend="inline">"And when they aroſe early in the morning,
behold in the Camp of the Aſſyrians, they were all dead corpſes.<note place="margin">Verſ. 35.</note>
               </q> The time would faile me, elſe I could
tell you of a <hi>Thundering Legion,</hi> That a whole Army was like to
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for want of water; <hi>Nothing remained then, but Prayer,</hi> and to
prayer they went; Prayers reached Heaven preſently, opened the Clouds, ſo
as they powred downe raine in abundance. Though the foole makes but a mock of
<hi>Prayer,</hi> as if it were like his, an abomination, a
<hi>mock-Prayer,</hi> yet I could tell you, the Adverſary has been ſo
wiſe, and knowing touching this matter, that ſhe has profeſſed, ſhe
feared the prevalency of Prayer, above what a mighty Army could doe, more the
prevalency of one man, of whom you might ſay, <hi>Behold he prayeth,</hi>
then the power of an Army of many thouſands. To draw-up toward a
concluſion, Prayer does all, at home and abroad, in <hi>private</hi> affaires
and in <hi>publique;</hi> It keeps the houſe, it locks the doores, it makes
two of one minde in an houſe, it bleſſeth the children, it makes all
things thrive there, it feeds the horſe, plowes the ground, houſes the
corne, makes all things proſper. What? Then the man may be lazy the while?
No, that cannot be, it makes a man moſt carefull and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the
uſe of all meanes, though he ſtayes and bottoms himſelfe upon none; his
reſt is upon God alone in Chriſt, there his Prayer fixeth: So for the
<hi>Private.</hi> For the <hi>Publique</hi> now, ſee how prevailing and
ſerviceable this <hi>Ordinance</hi> is, it binds Gods hand; when the ſword
is drawne, it ſheaths it againe; it ſtops the mouth of that
<hi>Devourer;</hi> it binds Kings in chaines, and Nobles in fetters of iron; it
makes warres to ceaſe, and lets the oppreſſed goe free; it limits proud
wrath, it ſets unto it its bounds, as to the raging Seas, <hi>So far and no
farther;</hi> But it never <hi>limits</hi> the <hi>Holy</hi> one of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> It ingages God to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very buſines, and ingageth the heart
to truſt in Him; and ſo there is an <hi>omnipotency</hi> in Prayer, &amp;c.
The ſervant of the Lord writeth upon every thing <hi>Askt of God,</hi> [for
what ſoever is not ſo <hi>Asked,</hi> cannot come to him as a Bleſſing]
and the <hi>gift of God.</hi> And if it be a Nationall Bleſſing [for that
his mouth is wideſt open, he is no body for himſelfe, but as the Church may
proſper] this he calls <hi>Naptali,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30.8.</note>
the child of <hi>my wraſtling,</hi> for with the <hi>wraſtling of God,</hi>
fervent ſtrong Prayers hath he gained this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing] And as it is in the
purpoſe of his heart to ſeek <hi>God</hi> ſtill, ſo he knows God heares
Prayers ſtill (i.e.) gives gracious returnes unto them. The Lord has ſpoken
good words, and comfortable, and they keep-up the <hi>Spirit of prayer</hi>
alwayes; ſo that his ſervants cannot be diſcouraged and faint in their
minds; <hi>Aske what you will, and it ſhall be done.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14.13 15.7.</note> O what unſpeakable grace is this! His
ſervants aske nothing, but according to their Fathers <hi>will</hi> (in
reference and ſubmiſſion thereunto.) And it is <hi>their
confidence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.14</note> that their <hi>Father
heareth them:</hi> And if they know this, <hi>That they are heard in
whatſoever they aske,</hi> then they know they <hi>have the Petitions they
deſire of Him.</hi> We muſt marke this with all obſervation, it will
reſolve us fully in all that follows. Thus and thus it has fallen out to the
Church in the <hi>North,</hi> thus in the <hi>South,</hi> and ſo in the
<hi>Weſt,</hi> and is not all this a great diſheartning to a praying
People? No, The contrary rather, all this puts <hi>heart</hi> into them, makes
their prayer more <hi>lively,</hi> and ſervent. It is with theſe
ſervants, as it was with their Maſter, the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> the
ſharper the <hi>Agony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.44.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the more <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
intended</hi> &amp; ſtretched out are the prayers. But I will anſwer
firſt to our <hi>Common Prayers,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we exſpect ſo preſent
anſwer, for we muſt note, that I am to ſpeake here <hi>ſpecially</hi>
to thoſe, that <hi>pray in Prayer,</hi> are the poore of the flock, a
<hi>deſtitute people</hi> in the enemies account, whom the Lord, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
in his Glory,<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.16,17.</note> as now he does, (and
he will be more glorious every day) does <hi>heare alwayes,</hi> even to their
<hi>will</hi> and <hi>weal</hi> both, whereof anon: To our more common Prayers
firſt, for we pray now; And doe we expect that God ſhould come-off roundly
with us, and anſwer all at the firſt? Have wee come-off roundly with him in
point of obedience, and good ſervice? I beleeve the moſt upright amongſt 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159075:4"/>us cannot ſay, <hi>Yes;</hi> Well then, and doe we looke,
that God ſhould <hi>turn</hi> to us the <hi>face</hi> preſently, and
Anſwer us in every thing, when we have been ſo narrow-mouth'd in asking,
ſo ſtraight-hearted in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, ſo ſlack in obeying,
<hi>turning</hi> the <hi>back</hi> upon God ſo long, and perhaps yet longer,
even at this preſent time; <hi>Regarding iniquitie in our hearts</hi> even
now, when we would have God <hi>regard our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> And would we be
regarded? Expect we, that God ſhould regard our Prayers now! Wee might
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect rather, that God ſhould ſtrike us dead upon our knees, and that He
has not done it, ſhould be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of wonder, and praiſe both. Has not God
waited when man would turn; and will not man be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to wait patiently,
when God will turn to him? Surely they, who <hi>Pray in Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">James
5.17.</note> indeed are a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People, theſe are a <hi>waiting</hi>
People; They can continue on their knees, or ſit downe aſtoniſhed, not
wondring, that God do's not anſwer them in every thing, but rather, that God
do's anſwer them in any thing, when they looke into themſelves, and upon
prayer as a prayer onely, and no more but a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which they have formed by
their owne ſtrength: And yet God is the hearer of Prayers, has heard their
Prayers, and given a gracious return to them, from time to time, ſo as they
can ſay, they never <hi>ſought God in vaine.</hi> To look no further back
now than into theſe three yeares by-paſt, up to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day; What
wonderfull Providences! Marveilous reſcues from the mouth of the Lyon, and
paw of the ſhee Beare! Admirable deliverances! ſtrange diſcoveries! What
were all theſe, but <hi>Naptalies</hi> all, the child, the fruit of <hi>my
wraſtling,</hi> does theſe praying People ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b.</note>But what will they ſay to theſe particulars, Theſe
diſcomfitures in the <hi>North,</hi> and theſe in the <hi>South</hi> and
<hi>Weſt;</hi> What will they ſay to <hi>Briſtoll?</hi> where was their
God then? Theſe <hi>mad-men</hi> will goe neare to ſay, theſe are their
<hi>Naptalies</hi> too, the fruit of their wreſtlings, of their groanes, and
ſtrong cryes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Yes indeed, they will ſay ſo,
and be confident in what they ſay, though their eares are too
<hi>chaſte</hi> to heare theſe Blaſphemies: I will begin where the Rimer
begins, with the <hi>North,</hi> and ſo goe compaſſe, and yet end
preſently: That bright Starre there, the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> hath ſhone
gloriouſly, &amp; does ſhine, notwithſtanding all the <hi>forces</hi> of
<hi>New-Castle,</hi> all the <hi>fraud</hi> &amp; <hi>treachery</hi> of the
<hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Sonne,</hi> to force out that <hi>light</hi> yet
that <hi>light</hi> doth ſhine, and its luſtre is <hi>ſet-forth</hi> by
all this force and fraud, and thereby made more glorious. And what is all this,
but a <hi>Naptali,</hi> the fruit of the Churches <hi>wraſtling</hi> with
their God, for and in behalfe of his ſervants there, and here. We muſt not
paſſe over lightly how gloriouſly God has been and is ſeen in the
<hi>North,</hi> an <hi>bearer of Prayers</hi> there, and here. How has the Lord
<hi>bent</hi> the hearts, inclined the ſoule of the people to his Cauſe?
What favour has He ſhewen his <hi>destitute</hi> people in the eyes one of
another! England lifted up the hand, to the moſt High God for Scotland, now
Scotland for England; They will joyne hand in hand, 
<q rend="inline">"To ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one minde,
ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel.</q> They will ſtand-up,
<hi>knit together all as one man,</hi> againſt common Adverſaries, the
Devill and his <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> with his <hi>Brutiſh Paſtors.</hi> Two
onely there were in the Aſſembly of Miniſters, who withſtood this
Covenant, a proud man, and as proud a <hi>Novice,</hi> neither of them cleared
in Judgement touching <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy</hi> (twins) by all that
has been written &amp; done theſe foure (I had almoſt ſaid foure hundred
yeares, I will ſay foureſcore) we know them, and, we hope, they know now
themſelves, what ſpirit they be of; The one a man of contention, The other
a <hi>childe,</hi> who will learne to hold his tongue, till he has learnt how
to ſpeake. <hi>Pacata Britannia eſt,</hi> England and Scotland, theſe
<hi>twaine</hi> once are <hi>one</hi> now, ſweetly compoſed in their God,
as a Citie Compact, and at unitie with it ſelfe, for they are in Covenant
with their God, and each with other; <hi>I am as thou art, my people as thy
people:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 18.3.</note> All will <hi>ſtick
together as one man,</hi> to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this common Adverſary. What ſhall
I ſay of this? The tongue of an Angel cannot utter it. But it is a
<hi>Naptali,</hi> the fruit of the Churches ſtrong wraſtling. Thus has God
don in the <hi>North,</hi> as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully in the <hi>South.</hi> How has he
got himſelfe a Name, &amp; made his Servant there a man of renowne, even the
Man of his Right hand! But then indeed, for I muſt ſpeak all, yet nothing
to diſhearten Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or to the Mans diſhonour: We fooles! we cannot have
a glorious Inſtrument, but we muſt dote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: We cannot have an
excellent man to ſtand up for us, but we will make a god of him; The Lord God
of gods ſaw this, our folly, and was angry; and ſo, when we would make man
an Idol, God would breake him to pieces. And what is all this? A
<hi>Naptali,</hi> a fruit of the Churches wraſtling; we ſhall ſee it more
cleare anon. But this is cleare now, for now we are taught a great leſſon,
<hi>To ceaſe from man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.22.</note> and, <hi>To
cleave to God,</hi> There-on to bottom our ſelves, and place our confidence.
And <hi>Briſtoll</hi> too, the impoveriſhing of that, and doing more, the
<hi>forcing</hi> of that Citie ſo, as never Citie has been ſo forced
(ſince there was a Citie upon the Earth) by the fierceſt Salvages and
moſt cruell Myrmidons. Indeed ſuch villanies, out-rages, notorious
violences are committed there, that I am at a ſtand what to ſay. But yet I
will call this a <hi>Naptali,</hi> a fruit of the Churches wraſtling; for we
muſt note, the Church does wraſtle with her God, intreats, that Deliverance
may come to his People: But ſhe does not <hi>limit the Holy One of
Iſrael;</hi> They doe not bind him to their time, their inſtruments, and
manner of working: They pray as men, they leave Him to worke, as a God, ſtill
with ſubmiſſion to his <hi>will,</hi> ſtill reſolving 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159075:4"/>all thither. And when they ſee what is the <hi>will</hi>
and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of their God, who <hi>does all things well,</hi> they
are well content. <hi>It is the Lord,</hi> ſay they, as <hi>Eli</hi> ſaid,
<hi>Let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam.
3.18</note> He has don it, His people, as <hi>Aaron</hi> in a ſad Caſe,
<hi>hold their Peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 10.3.</note> And yet they are
confident, God heares them alwayes, and has heard them in all that they asked,
for they asked nothing, but <hi>according to his will,</hi> (marke that,)
Therefore they have a confidence, that all, even this taking, and
<hi>forcing</hi> of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll</hi> ſhall be for the Churches
<hi>weale,</hi> greatly to advance the glory of their God, and the rejoycing of
his People. Their loſſes ſhall be their advantages, as to this time, ſo
till time ſhall be no more. So the wiſe God will order it, who (made a
<hi>Chaos,</hi> a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) brings order
out of the greateſt confuſion, life from the grave, and glory from the
Croſſe; They will truſt God, who would ſuffer no evill to be, but that
out-thence He does produce good; He will confound his Adverſaries by all
this, the Adverſaries lifting-up ſhall tend to his ruine; God gives him
ſcope, lets out the raines (gives him rope, he will ſtrangle himſelfe
with it) puts power into his hands, which he does exerciſe now with a rage,
that <hi>reacheth up to heaven;</hi> So high muſt his judgement reach,
<hi>even to the Skies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 51.9.</note> He has
exerciſed proud wrath, he has dealt treacherouſly: Now he ſees, as the
Ammonite did, <hi>That he ſtinckes before all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> There is a
notable diſcovery of the Adverſary at <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> his malice, his
rage, his luſt. The Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants there, ſome of them, are diſcovered too,
the treacherous Lawyer, and the vile Prieſt, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, a great mercy
all this, and all this the fruit of Prayer The Lord will diſcover his own
right hand alſo: Surely He that does nothing in vaine, has brought light out
of the womb of darkneſſe, will worke gloriouſly here, for His manner is
to make the moſt glorious light to appeare unto his Church, in that very
place (the <hi>Weſt</hi>) where it ſeemed to ſet. The <hi>Churches light
muſt riſe in obſcuritie:</hi> her <hi>darkneſſe muſt be as the
noone day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.10.</note> Doubtleſſe, the Lord
will worke gloriouſly about <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> and thoſe parts, we have a
<hi>word</hi> for it, that ſo He will doe, even a ſure word of Prophecie,
where thus wee reade, <hi>Wherefore ſhould they ſay among the People, Where
is their God?</hi> A cleare intimation, that ſo an Heathen people will ſay,
when God delivers his people into their hands, they will doe after their
manner, as the Heathen have done at all times, and now at <hi>Briſtoll,</hi>
reproach God and his People, ſaying, <hi>Where is their God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel 2.17.</note> What then? Then it followes, <hi>Then ſhall
the Lord be jealous for his Land, and pitie his People.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> Then! When? When the enemy is ſo proud, ſo
lifted up, that he dare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach God, aske where he is? When they deale ſo
proudly, as the Heathen did at <hi>Briſtoll:</hi> How dealt they there? I
tremble to tell the manner how, worſe then the Heathen did before them, or
their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who <hi>platted a Crowne of Thornes, and put it upon the head
of Chriſt:</hi> Theſe brutiſh men, worſe then thoſe Souldiers, have
plotted a worſe matter, and caſt a greater reproach upon the Lord in Glory.
<hi>When</hi> the Adverſary is ſo proud, <hi>Then</hi> will the Lord, as we
read before, and as it followes, <hi>He will no more make you a reproach
amongst the Heathen</hi> And does not the Lord pitie his People? Has he not
begun to take away their reproach? May it not be ſaid, and for
<hi>Glouceſter, What has the Lord done?</hi> The Adverſary is proud, for he
is very confident, he has an <hi>Arme like God,</hi> (as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
before him) he ſaid, <hi>I will take that Citie, my luſt ſhall be
ſatisfied upon them, I will draw my ſword, my hand ſhall deſtroy
them.</hi> Obſerve, I pray you, what the Adverſary ſayes; <hi>I
will,</hi> and <hi>I will,</hi> All ſhall be as he <hi>will,</hi> he never
asketh God leave: No, I warrant you, God <hi>is not in all his thoughts:</hi>
Tell him of God, and <hi>his will,</hi> he <hi>puffeth at you.</hi> Note it by
the way, that this is an infinite diſadvantage to the Adverſary: He is upon
a worke, which he cannot commit to God, he cannot adviſe with God about it,
all the counſell he takes is from the Devills Oracle, and he digs deep to
hide it, even unto hell; Therefore it is, that their deſigne many times,
proves <hi>abortive,</hi> like an untimely birth in the <hi>wild</hi> of
<hi>Kent:</hi> It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth it ſelfe, through haſte, like a poyſoned
Peice of <hi>Ordnance,</hi> which flies off, but breakes all to pieces, and all
about it. But when the Adverſary is ſucceſſefull and prevailes, it is
by treachery, helliſh devices, and contrivances, the <hi>depths of
Sathan:</hi> and ſo, prevailing by treachery, they oppreſſe the poore,
who cannot reſiſt them, they exerciſe proud wrath upon them, as Devills
incarnate, and as they did at 
<note n="*" place="margin">It is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious how miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous
theſe ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers were (their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty there, and every where, is
unuttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) they burnt as much wheat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to one man as was worth 700
pound.</note> 
               <hi>Ciceſter,</hi> and <hi>Bristoll.</hi> Reader, I ſay
againe, this is of infinite uſe, if thou wilt conſider this with it, the
infinite advantage the Church has above her Adverſaries, Shee can
<hi>Pray,</hi> while her Adverſaries do's <hi>Curſe</hi> and
<hi>Blaſpheme</hi> that worthy Name, by which (ſhee) is called; ſhee can
take Councell at Gods mouth, enquire, as <hi>David, of the Lord,</hi> at every
turn, ſtrengthen, ſtabliſh, beare up her ſelfe, upon an Almightie Arme
ſtill, here is an advantage, that cannot be expreſſed; but take all; the
Church (I meane ſtill a poore People, rich in Faith) have no <hi>will</hi> of
their owne, but what they have denied, and renounced, they have reſolved
their <hi>wills</hi> into Gods <hi>will,</hi> and they ſay ſtill, as they
ought to ſay, 
<q rend="inline">"If the Lord will, we ſhall live, and doe this
or that;<note place="margin">Jam. 4.15.</note>
               </q> Not ours, 
<q rend="inline">"but the will of the Lord be done;<note place="margin">Act. 21.14</note>
               </q> So they <hi>ceaſe</hi> evermore, as their
Brethren before them, concluding all their matters, and concernments under
<hi>Gods will.</hi> Here is an infinite advantage, which the Reader may note by
the way, and pardon the digreſſion. I returne now to our Adverſaries,
where we found them Blaſpheming the worthy Name, and ſpeaking thus proudly,
as we reade, <hi>Goe to now,</hi> ſay they, <hi>To day or to morrow,</hi>
within a very few<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159075:5"/>houres, <hi>we will goe into ſuch a
Citie</hi> (called <hi>Glouceſter</hi>) and, (kennell there, for they are
dogges) <hi>continue there this Winter,</hi> where we will whore, and drab, and
curſe, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme (God damne us) and ſhed bloud to our power; ſo
proudly they ſaid, ſo they <hi>will</hi> doe, ſuch a <hi>good will</hi>
they have, and ſo headlong it carries them. Now heare what the Lord will doe;
The Lord, who does <hi>caſt abroad the rage of his wrath, beholds every man,
that is proud, and abaſeth him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 40.</note> does
confound daring attempts, horrid rage, and curſed blaſphemy; decks
<hi>himſelfe with Majeſtie, and excellency,</hi> for the very purpoſe,
<hi>to reſiſt</hi> (to ſet himſelfe in Battle-Array againſt the
Proud)<note place="margin">James 4.6.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> He will ſhew himſelfe
glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in power now; the Right hand of the Lord will daſh in pieces the
enemy. Wee know the Lord has done it, though we had heard nothing touching that
matter, for God does reſiſt the proud; the God of Hoaſts ſets
<hi>Himſelfe in Battle-Array</hi> againſt ſuch haughty
<hi>Perſons;</hi> The <hi>loftie lookes of man ſhall be humbled:</hi> and
<hi>the haughtineſſe of Men ſhall be bowed downe,</hi> ſaith the
Lord;<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.11.</note> and as He ſaith, ſo He has
done; And He a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <hi>ſhall be exalted in that day.</hi> Wee will give now
all, that is due unto man, to his courage, to his faithfulneſſe; but we
muſt aſcribe Salvation to our God: He has mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched valiantly; He ſaw
there was none to helpe; Therefore <hi>His Arme brought Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, He has
repayed fury to his Adverſaries, recompences to His Enemies.</hi> In whom the
Church does truſt; He <hi>will yet deliver;</hi> He will goe on to ſhew
favour, to compleat His victories; He will take the matter into his owne hands;
He will doe, as his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſaid in their pride they would doe; The
Lord <hi>will purſue,</hi> He <hi>will overtake;</hi> He <hi>will divide the
ſpoyle.</hi> Theſe <hi>Balaams</hi> now are Poſting to another place, and
they Boaſt ſtill what they will doe there, They will doe to — as they
have done to <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> and as they would have done to
<hi>Glouceſter:</hi> So they will do, they have a good <hi>will</hi> unto it,
but God has them in his chaine, and has put a hooke in their noſtrells, and a
Bridle into their mouths, and He will ſend his <hi>men of warre after
them,</hi> carryed-on upon the wing of <hi>Prayer,</hi> put up from all the
corners of the world, and all his people there; carried alſo upon the wing of
Faith. The Church hopes, her people will not make Idolls of men any more; then
they ſhall be broken in pieces no more. Shee hopes, that her people are, if
not fit, yet fitting for deliverance; and her Adverſaries
<hi>rotten-ripe</hi> for deſtruction; if their iniquities not yet ful, yet
filling up to the brim, now they have reproached the Lord, now their mouths are
ſo wide open to utter blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſurely the Church ſees now their
<hi>day is coming;</hi> It is at hand. But ſhee has reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all touching
that matter, into Gods <hi>will,</hi> ſhee referres all to his time. If he
will make more breaches upon her, ſhe is humbled, and can <hi>accept of her
puniſhment,</hi> for ſhe knowes the time is coming, even the ſet-time,
when <hi>her Lord will make mak up his Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells,</hi> and <hi>Build the
Tabernacle of David</hi> which is fallen. And how ever the Lord may deale with
her for the preſent (it is His Prerogative Royall to deal with her as he
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: but mercy pleaſeth him) If He ſuffer His people to be longer
toſſed-up and downe like a Graſhopper, it is to ſettle them the
faſter upon the Rock. They know, <hi>God is Maſter of the end;</hi> What
ever the <hi>Premiſes</hi> are, he makes the <hi>Concluſion.</hi> So they
have concluded, and this is their confidence, What they looſe in the world,
they ſhall gaine in Heaven: All their loſſes here, ſhall be their
Advantages here and there; What they miſſe of here below, they ſhall
finde abundantly recompenced in Chriſt above; as their ſufferings are,
their conſolations ſhall be. In the meane time, they, as was ſaid,
<hi>limit not the Holy One of Iſrael;</hi> They leave him to His owne
<hi>will, worke,</hi> and <hi>time;</hi> They have reſolved their
<hi>will</hi> into His good Pleaſure; <hi>His will be done, Amen.</hi>
Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to He has done all things well, even when He broke His Armies to pieces,
He made them up again with advantage, two for one. Who would diſtruſt this
God? Surely<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159075:5"/>the Church will not. They will not <hi>forſake
their confidence;</hi> They have Prayed, and they have been heard ſtill, and
they will pray evermore, and are aſſured, that, when things are lower then
yet they are, or like to be, their Prayers will <hi>wheel-up</hi> all again,
and turne the Scene contrary to all expectation, but the godly mans. The
cauſe is Gods cauſe; the mannagers of it, His people; God will maintaine
his owne cauſe, and <hi>ſpare his People, according to the greatnes of His
mercy, Amen and Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt adde here; Whereas it is cleared now, what a mightie
Inſtrument Prayer is, how prevailing a weapon ever-more; And that it is the
Churches weapon, whereby ſhe turnes and wheeles about things, when they
ſeeme to be gone, quite fallen, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately loſt; When this is
cleared, This muſt not be concluded, That this is the Churches onely
<hi>weapon,</hi> ſhee muſt not uſe the <hi>Sword.</hi> Maſter
<hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cal Inſtit. li.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi>
20. <hi>ſect.</hi> 24, 25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> who has ſaid as much, I
beleeve, as any man in the world, touching the ſacred Majeſty of Kings, and
obedience due unto them; When he has ſaid all, as much as can be ſaid, and
yet no more; but what we all ſay, who ſpeake by the Booke of God, he
adjoynes, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſemper loquor.
Sect.</hi> 34.</note>
               <hi>All that I have ſpoken touching obedience to Kings,
or ſuffering from their hands, is ſpoken to private men;</hi> I doe not
meane the <hi>Ephori,</hi> who curbed the Lacedemonian power; nor the
<hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bunes,</hi> who righted the Romane People, when their Conſuls did
them wrong, &amp;c. Nor the Parliament in <hi>England;</hi> And there he has
theſe words, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si regibus impotenter graſſanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veant, eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſsimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia non</hi> carere
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmo. 32</note>
               <hi>If the Parliament there,</hi> (or any where) <hi>ſhall
winke at the Kings exorbitancy, cruſhing the poore, and grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faces
of the needy;</hi> If ſo, <hi>Then doe the Parliament deale treacherouſly,
They betray the poore of the flocke, and the truſt of the Kingdome.</hi>
There is but one Section more, and but a word out of it, which will ſtop
their mouths, who flap us in the mouth with this ſtill, <hi>That they have
ſworn obedience to their King.</hi> You muſt ever except this here, ſayes
Maſter <hi>Calvin; If it does not croſſe the Rule, and Gods command; That
you may ſatisfie men, you muſt not be ſo fool-hardy, as to incurre the
diſpleaſure of God, the God of Gods and Lord of Lords. Calvin</hi> has a
little more, but too much for me to ſet downe here; I would rather Kings did
read it, for it highly concerns them, even above their Crown.</p>
            <p>Three lines more muſt be added, they will be of infinite uſe.
The Adverſary here has carved-forth the Churches allowance, which ſhee
accepts, abundantly thankfull to her God. And now in this time of
diſtraction, ſo full of buſſel, and confuſion, the Church has but one
work to doe, which ſhee attends with all care and watchfulneſſe; 
<q rend="inline">"Their keeping their Spirit cleane, that their
Prayers may be pure; Their intercourſe, and commerce to Heaven kept open; and
their Communion intire with the <hi>Father and the Sonne.</hi>
               </q> This is
their worke, and they give their heart unto it. And now, though the Earth be
ſmitten, and ſtagger like a drunken man; Though it open wide whilſt ſhe
gives up her dead, and diſcovers her ſlaine, and vomits-up the
<hi>Hierarchy,</hi> with all their <hi>Brutiſh Paſtors,</hi> who have been
a burden to her ſo long, and cumbered her ground. Though <hi>a great
quaking</hi> fall upon the Kingdoms of the world, ſo as they be ſmitten
together, and broken to pieces; yet theſe People cannot be <hi>carefull,</hi>
not <hi>greatly moved;</hi> There <hi>is a River</hi> ſhall refreſh them in
this drougth, and an hand ſhall hold them faſt in this
<hi>Earth-quake,</hi> while the Lord is <hi>performing his whole worke upon
mount Sion, and on Jeruſalem;</hi> While he is making an <hi>end,</hi> and
drawing the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> which will be to the heart of His People,
gracious and glorious, Amen. So much to the firſt Blaſphemy, and the
concluſion therefrom; I will but name the other. 2. <hi>That theſe Praying
People are newly fallen mad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not <hi>newly</hi> ſure; they were anciently ſo mad as now
they are; ever ſince they could not run with thoſe, that blaſpheme them
ſo, into the ſame <hi>exceſſe of Riot with them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.4.</note> Ever ſince they did abominate <hi>Babylons
Wine,</hi> which, indeed, has made all the Earth<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159075:6"/>
               <hi>druncken,</hi> and <hi>the Nations mad, as at this day;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 51.7.</note> Ever ſince they kept their foot from the Path
of <hi>the deſtroyer,</hi> and loathed the way of <hi>Cain;</hi> ever ſince
they ſerved their God, according to the Rule of His will; Ever ſince they
could Pray <hi>indeed,</hi> (in the Holy Ghoſt) have they been accounted a
mad People. By thoſe that are mad indeed, mad upon their Idols; mad with rage
[as your poore flock of ſheep never are; But <hi>Armen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> and
<hi>Pecora,</hi> the <hi>Kine and Bulls of Baſhan, Nimrods,</hi> mighty
hunters before the Lord, great oppreſſors of the world, Beaſts-like-men,
theſe are mad, and ſo we ſay in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſpeech; But a <hi>mad flock
of ſheep</hi> was never heard off from the beginning to this day] Theſe are
harmleſſe, gentle, and meek, to a Proverb; and ſo meek they muſt be and
humble, for they are the poore of the flock, and God has humbled them, He has
<hi>meekned</hi> their hearts; for He has laid open their hearts unto them,
ſo they know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves now, and have ſo learnt Chriſt, that they are
lowly, meek, and vile in their own eyes, and content to be <hi>more vile and
baſe in their owne ſight.</hi> But they bleſſe God for this reproach
above many, for ſo they reproached Chriſt their Head; even ſo, <hi>He
hath a Devill, and is mad.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10.26</note> This makes
them leape for joy, becauſe their Lord Chriſt was ſo reproached: For as
they are made conformable to their Lord Chriſt in their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings from
the hand and tongue; ſo ſhall they be made conformable to Him in their
conſolations; They are as he was, ſo blaſphemed in the world; they
ſhall be <hi>as He is, in Glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2.</note>
What manner of Glory? Nay, had I the tongue of an Angel, I could not tell you
that, I can reade it as you can, That, when the Lord Chriſt, <hi>ſhall
appeare,</hi> theſe (poore of the flock) <hi>ſhall be like Him,</hi> and
ſee him <hi>as He is;</hi> like him, and as He is! I can ſay no more, but
admire: O the weight of glory! Onely, if you are of the number of thoſe
deſtitute ones, the <hi>poore of the flock,</hi> take your Fathers
bleſſing before you goe; <hi>Bleſſed are yee, when men ſhall revile
you, perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evill againſt you,
falſly for my ſake. Rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward
in Heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before
you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.11,12.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>Here is a vacant place, I will tell two ſtories, and fill it up,
one touching a <hi>perſon,</hi> the other a <hi>Thing:</hi> All is
heatheniſh, but we can make it Chriſtian, and very ſutable to all that is
ſaid before. <hi>Sophocles,</hi> a grave Poet indeed, lived a monaſtick
life, retired, and much in meditation. He is a <hi>fool</hi> and <hi>mad</hi>
both ſaid ſome, (they were his ſonnes) and ſo in our common ſpeech,
they would have begg'd their Father for a fool &amp; a mad-man, fit to have a
<hi>Guardian</hi> over him, unfit to be a guardian over others; his ſonnes
were fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter men, they thought: pretty youths! The father, after his manner,
ſaid little, but did much, and yet held cloſe to his <hi>work,</hi> &amp;
quickly ſhewed it to the Judges: 
<q rend="inline">"See, Sirs, ſaid he, is this the worke of a fool
&amp; a mad-man?</q> The application muſt be ſhort, the beſt men are
juſt ſo accuſed by (ſons I will not call them) baſtards not ſons,
becauſe they <hi>pray,</hi> they <hi>ſing Pſalmes,</hi> they maintaine
communion with their God. 
<note place="margin">Aug de
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I aſſure thee,
Reader, this was all could be charged againſt them in the worſt times, and
by their fierceſt enemies, theſe enemies themſelves being Judges: Well!
they will keepe to their work the cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer for this. And when their work
ſhall be manifeſt, as one day it ſhall, and the thoughts of all hearts:
Then, what ever the wicked think now, they will ſay then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <q rend="inline">"Theſe were the onely ſober &amp; wiſeſt
men:</q> So much of the <hi>perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>thing</hi> next, <hi>Archimedes</hi> had an Engine the
ſtrangeſt that ever was in the world. Therewith he defended a Citie bigger
then <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and defeated a ſtorming enemy there: To tell all
in a word, This man thus boaſted of himſelfe and this Engine, 
<q rend="inline">"Give me another earth, ſaid he, whereon to
ſet my foot, and I will pluck-up this earth, and throw it like a ball, Sea
and all.</q> Truely I cannot but ſmile at his conceit: As <hi>Diogenes</hi>
ſaid, 
<q rend="inline">"He would ſee how he could drinke out of his
hand, before he would throw away his diſh:</q> So this great Ingeneere would
have ſure footing on another <hi>earth,</hi> before he would caſt away
this; but he did expreſſe the energie and ſtrange working of his Engine
very well. There are a people, who have as ſtrange an Engine as this: which
we call (nothing but) Prayer: Ile tell you what it will doe, defend a Citie
from a ſtorming Adverſary: More then ſo; It will pluck up earth to
heaven, and pluck down heaven to earth: I have neither time nor ſpace to
ſay more, but ſo it will doe.</p>
            <trailer>An End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
